Guide to the Ralph Mayer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1912-1990
  - Leftover from selection loaned for Viking list, 1950-1959 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Leonardo, 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Letters from 1961 news release on Artists Technical Research Institute (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Levinson, Henry W., 1943 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Litter, David
    - 1969 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Laboratories, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Luminous coatings, 1942 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - M, 1976-1980 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence with Lawrence J. Majewsky and Fred Machetanz.
  - Man of the year, National Art Materials Trade Association (NAMTA), 1951-1969 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Maroger, Jacques, 1944-1973 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Masonite, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Mayer archives at the University of Delaware, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Mayer, Bena
    - Letters and cards, 1979-1984 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Regarding Ralph Mayer Center and University of Delaware, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - University of Delaware, 1961-1985 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Mayer, Ralph
    - Conservation, 1951-1973 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Exhibitions, painting at the Metropolitan Museum of Art under 'Artists for Victory' show, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Presentation, 1966-1972 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Writing, 1951-1954 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Mayer, Virginia, 1976-1982 (Box 19, Folder 21-22)
  - Mellon, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Memorabilia, 1921-1952 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Memorabilia a la framer, 1964-1979 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art letter to Bressler, important, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Mint standard, 1965-1977 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    Includes letters with assorted correspondents.
    - 1931-1953 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - 1940-1951 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - 1940-1955 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 1957-1962 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - 1968-1977 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - 1978 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, letters, 1949 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Conservation, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Notes, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Notes on canvas for portraits, 1933-1965 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Organizations, 1941-1949 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Papers, 1965-1977 (Box 20, Folder 13-14)
      Includes biographical material on Mayer and printed material enclosed within letters to assorted correspondents.
    - Writings, 1921-1948 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Money from Penguin, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - My efforts to explain squabble regarding Ralph Mayer Center, 1984-1987 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - National Art Materials Trade Association (NAMTA), 1969-1971 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - New School and notes on The Painter's Craft, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Note on inquiries, Circa 1912-1990 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Number 2, 1954-1979 (Box 20, Folder 22-23)
  - O, 1949-1959 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Oberlin, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Oils testing, 1954-1958 (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - Oils, vegetal, very old, 1912-1950 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Original letter from first sponsors, 1954-1961 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Others using The Artist's Handbook material as reference, 1961-1971 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - P, 1955-1975 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Paintings to go to University of Delaware, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Pending, including toxic American Artist articles, toxicity, 1976-1981 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Personal, 1938-1977 (Box 21, Folder 7-8)
  - Philosophical Library, Incorporated - Dictionary of the Arts, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Pigment handbook, 1968-1969 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Postcards, 1959-1962 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Premature varnishing, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Prochim, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Prominent painters - Fiene Sloan, Hammer Bishop, and others, 1941-1970 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Ralph Mayer as a painter, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Regarding lecturer position, 1930-1943 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Requests for opinions, information, 1948-1976 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Restoration - letter from Elmer Rede or the Whitney Museum, 1941-1964 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Return letters - journal and personal correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - R, 1936 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Rowney, T. H., 1964-1974 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Rowney, T.H., Reinhold, Roberson, and Rogers, 1963-1965 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Royalties, 1968-1988 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - Royalties statements, 1980-1988 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - S, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - S-T, 1931-1955 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Includes letters from Trinidad, Paul Sample, and Mary P. Thayer.
  - Selected letters, 1939-1955 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Serigraph, 1942-1973 (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
  - Silicon esters, 1941-1951 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Simon's rock, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Six letters from Ralph Mayer, Circa 1912-1990 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Includes letters from Ralph Mayer to Bena Frank Mayer and unidentified correspondents. Also includes notes by Ralph Mayer on art history and materials.
  - Slide lecture, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Some interesting side-lights for Marcia Burch - The Painter's Craft, 1966-1978 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Squabble over varnish, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Standards, 1961-1970 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Stoner, Joyce Hill, 1984 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Storage Warehouse, 1940 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Stretchers and Mayer writings, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Technical, 1960-1963 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Technical questions
    - 1979 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - 1979-1989 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Circa 1912-1990 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Termination league, 1988-1989 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - The Artist's Handbook
    - 1936-1961 (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - 1938-1972 (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - 1971-1979 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Letters regarding The Artist's Handbook and The Painter's Craft, 1947-1981 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Rejections, 1938-1946 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Revision, 1979-1981 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - The Artist's Technical Research Institute, 1940-1977 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Thomas, Mrs. Seth, 1950 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - 3M sample offer, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Toch, Henry M., 1930 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Toxicity, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Un, 1974-1978 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    Includes letters to Mayer with inquiries on artist's materials.
  - University of Delaware
    - 1985 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1983-1985 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Termination, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Van Nostrand
    - First edition, 1946-1972 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Reinhold (Litton Educational Publications), 1970-1973 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Second edition, 1963-1966 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Velvet painting, 1968-1970 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Very special mediums - Bocour contract, 1961 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Viking Press
    - 1940-1950 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Best, Marshall, 1940-1971 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Contracts, 1940, 1969; 1969 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Copy of standards, 1968-1988 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Copyright and letters, including important material about The Painter's Craft, 1949-1989 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Early correspondence, 1967-1977 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Mailing list - reviews, 1980-1982 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Odds and ends, 1974-1980 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - The Painter's Craft and contract, letter about dictionary, 1966-1976 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Revision, 1979-1981 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Royalties and film strip, 1967-1976 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Second edition, 1957-1959 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Third edition, 1970-1979 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Work on 4th edition, 1973-1981 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Watson-Guptill, 1964-1973 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - White lead, 1972-1978 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Windsor and Newton, 1977 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - World Book Encyclopedia, 1954-1968 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - X-Z, 1966-1974 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Xerox copies of notes and letters, 1972-1973 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Zerbe, Karl, 1949-1971 (Box 24, Folder 17)
- Personal papers, 1870-1991
  - Archives of American Art, Washington, D. C., 1966-1978 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Awards and certificates, 1944-1976 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Awards, Yaddo, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Bena Mayer's passport, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Bena's will, codicils, and trusts - obsolete, 1974-1991 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Book, 1871 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Composition notebook, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence regarding estate and death certificate, 1979-1983 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Efforts with hospital, 1979-1987 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Friends and colleagues, 1981-1982 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    Includes slides.
  - Hospital, 1979-1987 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Keepsakes, 1951-1971 (Box 25, Folder 12-13)
  - Letters, bills, fundraising plan, 1979-1985 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Mailing lists, 1977-1988 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Medical, 1987 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Membership to art organizations, 1927-1963 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous objects, 1870-1945 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Notebooks, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Notebook and book in German, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Record book, 1951-1952 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Record of silver purchases, 1944-1970 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Renssalaer booklets, 1962-1969 (Box 26, Folder 6, Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Renssalaer, 1959-1962 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    Includes photographs.
  - Robinson, Leo, receipts, 1937-1970 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbooks, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
  - Sketches, Circa 1870-1991 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Tax management booklet, 1988 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - The Courtship of Miles Standish, 1905 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Toch, May, 1920-1940 (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1929-1977
  - General, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 1-8)
  - Around New York, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Changewater, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Demonstrations, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Fire Island, 1947 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Forsythe Street, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Laboratory, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Lake Harbor, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 16-17)
    - Details, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Paintings, 1929 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Pennsylvaneous, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 20)
      Includes negatives.
  - Mounted, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 28, Folder 21, Box 29, Folder 1-3)
  - Mounted on wood, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - 106th Street, east views, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - The Painter's Craft
    - Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Glass slides, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 32)
    - Negatives, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Paintings
    - 1964 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Important, 1966 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Negatives, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Painting techniques, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 29, Folder 12, Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Pastel stroke negatives, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Pearl Street elevated, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Personal, 1938-1977 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Peterborough
    - Grone St. Bridge, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Noone Mill, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Sand Mountain, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Photographs and negatives, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Photographs and some notices, 1970-1976 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Rigamenti stretchers, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - San Trovaso, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Small photographs, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Street and sketch, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - Stone Studios, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Truro and Provincetown, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Truro and sketches, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - Union Island, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - Vineyard, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 19)
  - Washington, New Jersey, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - Watrin's Glen and trip, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  - Williamsburgh Brooklyn vista, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 22)
  - Woodstock, Circa 1929-1977 (Box 30, Folder 23)